<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The loue of the soule Made by G.M.</title>
            <author>Martin, Gregory, d. 1582.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1597</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07101</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17504</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105435</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841163</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841163</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5725</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07101)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5725)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 929:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The loue of the soule Made by G.M.</title>
                  <author>Martin, Gregory, d. 1582.</author>
                  <author>Martin, Gregory, d. 1582. Treatyse of Christian peregrination. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[52] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Fr. Garnet's second press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Roane [i.e. London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1578 [i.e. ca. 1597]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>G.M. = Gregory Martin.</note>
                  <note>Reprinted from his: A treatyse of Christian peregrination.</note>
                  <note>Actual imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C D⁴ (-D3-4).</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5725:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5725:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LOVE OF THE SOVLE</p>
            <p>Made by G. M.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>christogram</figDesc>
               <q>IHS</q>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at Roane 1578.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:5725:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5725:2"/>
            <head>TO MY LOVING AND beſt beloued Siſters.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>EERE SISTERS my care, my loue, and of all worldlye thinges (next to my good MOTHER) my greateſt comforte and ioy. Vnleſſe you did thinke that I doe moſt har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily loue you, you coulde not alwaies heeretofore haue decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red your exceedinge great loue ſoe plentifullye towardes mee, for the which Almightie God
<pb facs="tcp:5725:3"/> reward you. This my loue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not a naturall affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on onely, but ſyncere and true Charitie forceth mee to wiſhe vnto you my louing SISTERS, not only many worldly commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, which (God be thanked) you lacke not: but much more, all Spirituall treaſure and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly riches, whereof you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not haue greate ſtore, becauſe you dwel not where it groweth.</p>
            <p>I know good SISTERS, that you meane well, and moſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling are you to doe that which might pleaſe God: but in good ſooth you are out of the way, &amp; therefore the further you holde
<pb facs="tcp:5725:3"/> on, the further you are from your iorneis ende, and the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from Heauen. The wiſe man ſaith: Prouerbs. 14. <hi>There is away which ſeemeth to a man right but the end thereof leadeth to deſtruction.</hi> Beare with me if I write bouldly, and tell you the truth plainely. I am your Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I loue you as nature bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me, not onely in wordly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte, but much more towards God. Your ſoules are deare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me: my heart alwaies mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to thinke vpon your dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous ſtate wherein you ſtand. O good SISTERS, the paine, of Hell exceedeth all torments,
<pb facs="tcp:5725:4"/> and that fire ſhall burne for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Happie are they that keepe them ſelues by GOD his great goodneſſe within the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Church, for out of it there is no hope of ſaluation: And moſte happie are they that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing bene out of this Church by the wicked perſwaſions of falſe Preachers, when that it pleaſeth God to ſende them trew teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: will not remaine obſtinate: but follow good exhortations, and good holſome doctrine, and ſo returne againe as obedient Children to Chriſt their father, and to the Church theire Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who are alwaies ready to
<pb facs="tcp:5725:4"/> receiue them: remembring that which a moſt ancient &amp; learned Father writeth. S. Auſtin in the 88. Pſal. <hi>He can neuer account God to be his Father, who will not haue the Church to be his mother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you aske me what this Church is, that is called Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke, and how you may knowe it, behold the true and certaine markes thereof, and your ſelfe iudge whether you be within it or no. This Church is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of all true Chriſtians, which began in Chriſt and his Diſciples at Ieruſalem, &amp; from thence, grewe and multiplied throughout the wholle world,
<pb facs="tcp:5725:5"/> according as it is ſaide in the Pſalme: <hi>their ſound</hi> (ſpeaking of the Apoſtles) <hi>is gone out into the whole world, &amp; their wordes into the ends of the earth.</hi> Pſa. 18. ve. 5 <note place="margin">The firſt marke of the chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ch is to be vſible</note> So that the firſt marke of the true Church is, that it muſt grow and multiplie, be ſeene, &amp; appeare alwaies as a light in the world: and therfore Chriſt calleth it <hi>A Citie builded vpon a hill, which cannot be hid.</hi> And the bleſſed Martyr S. Cip. ſaith: The Church being light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the brightneſſe of our Lord, doth reach forth her bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes throghout the whole world
<pb facs="tcp:5725:5"/> And S. Auſt. beſides many other places to this purpoſe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pareth Chriſt &amp; his Church, to that <hi>ſtone which was cut out of a hill with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mens ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, &amp; after grew to be a mighty mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tain, ſo that it filled the whole earth.</hi> For vndoubtedly this ſtone whereof the Prophet ſpeaketh in CHRIST, who was borne of a Virgine without the helpe of man, &amp; is now growne from a few Apoſtles and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to an infinite number of Chriſtian people in all countries confeſſing one Faith, &amp; one Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe: and this is the Catholicke Church, whereof your CREED telleth, and teacheth you to ſay.
<pb facs="tcp:5725:6"/> 
               <hi>I beleeue the Catholicke Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs ſee now whether this marke doth agree to your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in England, who cal them ſelues Proteſtants: or to vs who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it pleaſeth them to call Papiſts. Firſt, they call them-ſelues in their books the Engliſh Church, that is to ſay, of that faith which is profeſſed in England: but we are of the Catholicke Church, that is, of ſuch a faith as is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed in France, in Spaine, in Flanders, Brabant, Zeland, &amp;c. In a great part of Germanie, in all Italy, and beyond, wherſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer there be Chriſtians, and is preached in the Indians, that
<pb facs="tcp:5725:6"/> neuer heard of Chriſt before, &amp; increaſeth wonderfullye. And within theſe fortie yeeres, in England, Scotland, Ireland, Denmarke, and Germany, there was no other faith openly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed but ours. And now alſo in all theſe countries, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are there thinke you of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Catholickes that wiſhe for the olde religion againe with all their heart, and follow the new only for feare? Nay how many are there eſpecially in England that do yet openly profeſſe the Catholike faith?</p>
            <p>Aske good Siſters aske, and you ſhall learne that all the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb facs="tcp:5725:7"/> not onely of London, but of England are full of them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they will not yeelde to theſe new proceedings, nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taminate their ſoules with this new ſeruice, and leaue the olde true and Catholicke faith: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides a number of ſundrie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, which are dead in priſon: namely twentie three Biſhops, all depriued of their liuing theſe twentie three yeeres, and now but two of them aliue: I omitt Doctours, Deanes, Archdeacons Knightes, Squires, partly in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, partly departed the realme and forſaking all, rather then they will forſake God, and his
<pb facs="tcp:5725:7"/> moſt true and vndoubted Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. This is true (good Siſters) as knoweth God, you ſeldome heare of theſe thinges, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you thinke eyther there is no other Religion but that cold ſeruice without all comfort and deuotion which you ſee in your pariſhe Church, or you thinke that muſt needes, bee the beſt, becauſe you are not taught any other: whereas you ſee (if you beleeue me) that all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome almoſt is of another Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. And therefore this is the Catholicke Church, and yours is worthely called by your owne miniſters, the Church of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.
<pb facs="tcp:5725:8"/>
               <note place="margin">The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d mark is ſuc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſion.</note> But this ſhall better appear if I giue you an other marke of the true and Catholicke Church, which is, that it may continue for euer, and from the firſt beginning, which was in Chriſt &amp; his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, neuer to faile, but to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare &amp; be ſeene ſtil as a City vp on a hill, or a light in the world: For Chriſt ſaid. <hi>I will be with you vnto the end of the world.</hi> Mat. 28 And againe: <hi>I will ſend you an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other comforter, the ſpirit of truth who ſhal romaine with you for euer</hi> And vnto Peter. <hi>vpon this Rocke will I build my Church, and the gates of Hell ſhall not preuiale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:5725:8"/> it.</hi> Mat. 16. That is to ſay, the Diuell and all his Miniſters, ſhall neuer ſo preuaile againſt this Church, but that it will ſtill appeare and profeſſe one &amp; the ſame faith: So that there ſhall be no time wherein this faith &amp; this Church is not. Now marke good Siſters I pray you hartely, whether your Church and your Engliſh religion hath bene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in the world ſince Chriſt his time. I will ſpeake vnto you as before God, and as I ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere before him at the latter day, and therfore I requeſt you to marke well my wordes, and to conſider of them. A whole
<pb facs="tcp:5725:9"/> thouſand &amp; fiue hundred yeeres after Chriſt, your Engliſh reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion was not heard of in anie part of the worlde, but I tolde you before, that the true Church muſt continue for euer, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare alwaies, vnleſſe you think CHRIST is falſe of his promiſe. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> began your religion them Forſooth about fiftie veeres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone, by one <hi>Martin Luther</hi> in Germanie a Friar: who as well for other vngodly reſpectes, as alſo becauſe hee would needes marrye, and breake his vowe which he had made of chaſtitie, beganne to preach againſt the Pope, and againſt the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke
<pb facs="tcp:5725:9"/> Church, and becauſe hee taught greate libertie, as that Princes ought not to reuerence the Pope, that all Prieſtes might marry, that no man need to faſt, and ſuch like: he found many Diſciples in Germany, and hath vnto this day carnall and fleſhly men that loue their own pleſure more then the will of God, and his holy Church.</p>
            <p>But will you know what ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of man this was? Forſooth being examined by learned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> concerninge his doctrine, hee was ſo preſt and ſo angred with the force of truth, that he ſaide in a great rage. <hi>This quarrell was
<pb facs="tcp:5725:10"/> neuer begun for Gods ſake, neither for his ſake ſhall it be ended.</hi> Will you know further that he wrote againſt the Pope for malice and not for conſcience? him ſelfe in his letter to <hi>ARgentmenſes</hi> ſaith: <hi>I neither can deny, neither will I, that if Carolſtadius or any other man cold fiue yeres agon haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded me, that in the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is nothing but bread and wine, he might haue deſerued of me great thanks: for I laboured in that mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter very carefully, knowing right well that by that meanes, I might much haue hindred the Popes au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tority.</hi> Marke that this man wold gladly haue found ſome what a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:5725:10"/> the bleſſed Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but a long time he could not, till at length the Diuell had taught him to write againſt the Maſſe, as him ſelfe witneſſeth in his books, <hi>de Miſſa angulari.</hi> where he telleth what talke he and the Diuell had togither. Much more could I tell you of this man: but of this litle you may iudge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you may adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture to build your faith vpon this man, who liued within theſe fiftie yeares, and to forſake the ancient faith of all Chriſtendome: continued from Chriſt vntill this day: for it is moſt certaine that from this man came your newe Religion
<pb facs="tcp:5725:11"/> into England, but not immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly at the firſt when hee began to preach, <note place="margin">Maieſties Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wrote a learned Book againſt Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the Pope. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke him not vpon religion or conſcience but vpon diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure.</note> for King Henry the eight, wrote a learned booke ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie earneſtly againſt The Queens him, which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be ſeene, but long after, partlie when the King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to take diſplea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure againſt the Pope, becauſe he might not be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried &amp; vnmaried as he liſt, partlye &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially, when King Edward beeing in the beginning of his raigne, but a very Childe, was ouerruled by wicked Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſellers
<pb facs="tcp:5725:11"/> to maintaine ſuch a Religion, as might beſt agree to their carnal appetite. This was the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of your Religion, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning I ſaye, for as for King <hi>Henry,</hi> he went nothing ſo far as they are now come: but where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as for his pleaſure he had put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Popes authority, &amp; for his profite had plucked downe Abbeies, he let all other pointes in manner remaine as before, &amp; for this repented before he died as it is knowne, if not? woe be to him that euer he was bornes for there in the nexte worlde, good Siſters, Kings &amp; Queenes come to their accountes, as well
<pb facs="tcp:5725:12"/> as you and we poore folkes.</p>
            <p>I could here tell you of many learned and vertuous men that were then put to death, becauſe they woulde not yeelde to the King in his vnlawfull dooinges: knowing right well that it was all contrary to the law of God. Amongſt who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were theſe two: the Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter</hi> the moſt vertuous and beſt learned of all the clargie, as appeareth by his bookes. And Sir <hi>Thomas Moore</hi> Lord Chauncel or of England a Lay-man, who for his vertue, wiſedome and learning paſſed all temporal men that euer were in that realme, as appeareth by
<pb facs="tcp:5725:12"/> his learned works written in the Engliſh tongue, but nowe not ſuffred to be read: becauſe they teach the Catholick faith: ſome man will tell you, that they were beheaded for treaſon: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue him not, vnleſſe it be trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to obay God rather then Princes, ſurelye other treaſon they committed none. <note place="margin">The .3. mark is vnitie.</note> One marke more I will ſhew you to diſcerne the true church, &amp; that in fewe wordes: but ſo plaine that your ſelfe will confeſſe it. To know the Catholick Church this is a certaine and an vnfalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble marke, if it be in vnitie and
<pb facs="tcp:5725:13"/> concord if it haue an agreement &amp; conſent of harts &amp; opinions: that is to ſay, if it haue but one faith &amp; religion: For of the true Church it is ſaid, <hi>The whole mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of beleuers had one hart &amp; one mind.</hi> Act. 5. And ſaint Paul ſaith. <hi>One God, one faith, one Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</hi> Eph. 4. And againe. <hi>God is not a God of diſſentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but of peace &amp; vnitie.</hi> 1. Cor. 14. Looke now and conſider the ſtate of your Proteſtantes in England onely, are they all of one religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Haue you not among them ſome Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans, ſome Caluiniſts, ſome Puritanes, all agreeing againſt the Pope, and each diſagreeing
<pb facs="tcp:5725:13"/> one from the other? Doe not your Lutherans preach yea be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Queene, not without greate thankes for their labour, that the Body of Chriſt is really preſent in the Sacrament? And doe not your Calueruſts preach cleane contrarie, that there is only bread and wine? And as for your Puritanes do not they preach and write ſo far contrary from the other two, that they are now forbidden to preach &amp; caſt into priſon, and put from all liuings? Yea the communion booke it ſelfe, doth it not now ſay clean contrary to that which it ſaid in the latter end of King
<pb facs="tcp:5725:14"/> Henry his time? Then you were expreſly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded to beleeue that vnder each kind, of bread, &amp; wine, are contained the body and blood of Chriſt, now it is a petty treaſon to ſay ſo: I ſpeake not heere of Denmarke, of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neua, of other citties in Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, who are all Proteſtants, and are differing among them ſelues and from you. I haue onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared how great diuerſity and diſagreing there is among your Proteſtants at home within one litle Iland: which is ſo euident, and ſo far from good Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that it may bee vnto you a verie certaine and ſure token,
<pb facs="tcp:5725:14"/> that the true faith can not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, which hitherto can not agree in one faith, each con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning the others opinion.</p>
            <p>Thus (dearly beloued, and my very louing Siſters) I haue giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you certaine generall mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes to learne the true Church: To write all were infinite, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all bookes are full of our religion, I truſt hereafter to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct you in euery point as you would deſire, and I pray GOD giue you grace, that you may deſire it: All at once would be too tedious: in the meane time remember theſe two thinges: <hi>When your religion began, and by
<pb facs="tcp:5725:15"/> whome,</hi> &amp; how it came at length into England. This is the yeare of Chriſt, a thouſand fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred eightie and three. Luther begane to preach within theſe fiftie yeares: If he preached the truth, &amp; all before him were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued, where was the Church of Chriſt in all the world for a thouſand &amp; fiue hundred yeares before? and how is Chriſt true of his promiſe, that ſaid: <hi>I will re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maine with you for euer, &amp; the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt ſhal teach you all truth &amp; the gates of hell ſhal not preuail a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</hi> But for our Church, that is to ſay, the Catholick Church, we can ſhew how it is growne,
<pb facs="tcp:5725:15"/> and continued from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles vntill this day, and neuer fayled: we can recken you from time to time, Councels, Biſhops Doctours, infinite numbers of good Chriſtians of all ages that were all of our faith, and of our Church. Can your Miniſters de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but that Saint <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth praying to Saintes? Or that S. <hi>Ierome</hi> calleth the Biſhop of Rome, Supreame head of the whole Church vnder Chriſt? Or that S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> praied for his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being dead? Or that he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured the Reliques of S. <hi>Steue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Or that S. <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaide Maſſe? Or that S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, before
<pb facs="tcp:5725:16"/> the wordes of conſecration it is bread and wine, but after the wordes are ſpoken by the Prieſt, it is the very body and blood of Chriſt? or that all Chriſtians in S. <hi>Auſtins</hi> time? did worſhip the bleſſed Sacrament? Or that the ſecond Councell of <hi>Nice,</hi> did many hundred yeares, alow the vſe of Images, for the memorie and repreſentation of Chriſt &amp; his Saintes, condemning Image breakers. Or that Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> was an Abbot and had Monkes vnder him, as in Catholicke Countries now a daies? can they denie but that all this is true? and dare they deny theſe
<pb facs="tcp:5725:16"/> vertuous Fathers, and Doctors of the Church to be now Saints in heauen?</p>
            <p>O my good Siſters, that you could vnderſtand their bookes and theire writinges that you might your ſelues ſee what they ſay, and what wonderfull men they were, endued with the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of God exceedingly aboue other, euen good men, much more then your licentious lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, I doubt not but you would ſuſpect your new Doctors, and follow theſe: you ſhoulde per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue they had the Scriptures at their fingers ends, they knew right well the meaning &amp; ſenſe
<pb facs="tcp:5725:17"/> therof, night and day by faſting and praier, and chaſte life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching God that they might vnderſtand and truely expound his worde. O what a difference is there betweene them and theſe new preachers? Siſters, I appeale to your conſciences, whether will you, or ought you to truſt in the expoundinge of Scripture, your yong vnlearned and fleſhly miniſters, or theſe auncient, moſt ſkilfull, and moſt vertuous Fathers.</p>
            <p>When Chriſt ſaied: <hi>Take eate, this is my Body.</hi> All theſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers ſay and agree, that it was his Body in very deed: your mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters
<pb facs="tcp:5725:17"/> tell you it was but Bread and Wine. When Chriſt ſayed to Peter: <hi>Thou art Peter, that is a rocke, &amp; on this rocke wil I build my Church.</hi> Mat. 16. Theſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſay that Peter was made head of the Church, and after him all his ſucceſſors in the See of Roome where Peter was the firſt Biſhop. Your Miniſters tell you that Peter had no more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence then the other Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and therfore the Biſhoppe of Roome hath no more autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie then an other Biſhop hath. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt ſaid to his Apoſtles: <hi>Receaue yee the Holy Ghoſt what ſoeuer yee doe looſe in earth, ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:5725:18"/> be looſed in heauen, &amp; what ſoeuer ye do binde in earth ſhall be bound in heauen.</hi> Theſe Fathers ſay that Chriſt gaue to his Church auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to remitt ſinne by the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrie of the Prieſt, to all ſuch as do truely repent, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will haue the people go to confeſſion: your miniſters haue taken that comfortable Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Pennance away altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. When <hi>Raphael</hi> the Angell ſaith in the twelfth chapter of Tobias: <hi>That he did offer vp Tobi as praier to Almightie God.</hi> And when in the ſecond booke of <hi>Macchabes</hi> the 15. chap. <hi>Onias</hi> the Prieſt ſaith of <hi>Ieremie</hi> being
<pb facs="tcp:5725:18"/> dead. <hi>This is hee that prayeth much for his people, and for the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Citty:</hi> theſe Fathers ſay, that the Angels and Saintes do pray for vs, and that we may pray to them: your miniſters do not ſtick to ſay, that theſe bookes of <hi>Toby</hi> and the <hi>Machabees</hi> are ſcant good Scripture.</p>
            <p>Many other thinges like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe, I could reckon, but I ſhould be too long, fearing leaſt I ſhould weary you: theſe fewe are ſufficient to giue you to taſt of ſuch markes as may ſhew you the Catholicke Church. Theſe and many other greate reaſons doe keepe all good Chriſtians
<pb facs="tcp:5725:19"/> within the church. Theſe things make ſo many Catholicks, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to haue ſuffered death: part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to haue died in priſon: partly to continue in priſon ſo manie yeares: partly to forſake theire pleaſant countrie, theire deere friends, and to liue to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience among ſtrangers, being thought of many worldly men to be very fooles for ſo doing: but they knowright wel that the wiſdome of this world is fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes before GOD. And Chriſt ſaith, <hi>He that loueth father &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, ſiſter &amp; brother, better than me, is not worthy of me. Mat. 10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Siſters geue me leaue to tell
<pb facs="tcp:5725:19"/> you ſomewhat of my ſelfe, not for any bragge, but the more to moue you and to giue God all the praiſe for his great goodnes towards me. It pleaſed my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents to bring me vp in learning as you knowe, as I was not the beſt, ſo I was at all times not counted the worſt amongſt my fellowes and companions: ſome ſmall eſtimation I had in Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford aboue my deſert, more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes when it pleaſed the <hi>Duke</hi> to make me though vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, Tutor to the <hi>Earle</hi> his ſonne: as long as his grace did proſper, I liued in his houſe to my conſcience without trouble:
<pb facs="tcp:5725:20"/> when he was in the Tower, and other men ruled his houſe, I was willed to receiue the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, or to depart: if I woulde haue yeelded, I had very large offers which I need not tell. It pleaſed God to ſtay me ſo with his grace, that I choſe rather to forſake all then to doe againſt my beleefe, againſt my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, againſt my conſcience, againſt the lawe of Almightie God: For a time I lay ſecretlie in England, afterwardes I came beyond the Seas into theſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke countries, out of ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me and hereſie: for the which I doe thanke Almightie GOD
<pb facs="tcp:5725:20"/> much more, then for all the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimation that I had, or might haue had in England. Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer my eſtate is heere, I doe more eſteeme it, then all the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of England as it now ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth.</p>
            <p>And were I ſo mad think you to forſake all preferment, all li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings, all eſtimation, to liue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my good mother, from you my louing ſiſters, &amp; your huſbands, from other my deare friendes &amp; companions, out of mine owne moſt pleaſant countrie, would I do this thinke you, but that my learninge and my conſcience, telleth me, that to follow your
<pb facs="tcp:5725:21"/> Religion is preſent daunger of body and ſoule, and to be in the Catholicke Church is the onely way to ſaluation? Fie vpon all worldly riches, when the ſoule is in danger, nothing is ſo preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as the ſoule: firſt ſeeke for the Kingdome of heauen, &amp; for other things as it pleaſeth God. O that I might vnderſtand once that you were of my mind, and of the Catholicke religion: O my hart would leape for ioy, to conſider that although we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not liue together vppon earth, yet we may hereafter meete in heauen: which is impoſſible as long as we diſagree in faith. S.
<pb facs="tcp:5725:21"/> Paul ſaith. <hi>There is one God, one Faith, one Baptiſme.</hi> S. Auſtin ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, ſpeaking of one <hi>Emeritus, He cannot be ſaued but in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tholicke Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doe you thinke it ſufficient to beleeue in the Father, the Son, &amp; the holy Ghoſt? Harken what S. Auſtine ſaith in the 88. Pſalme. <hi>What doth it profite thee, if thou confeſſe the Lord? If thou honor God? if thou prech &amp; praiſe him? if thou acknowledge his Son? if thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſ that he ſitteth at the right hand of his Father? what doth this profit thee, if thou blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme his Church? S. Athanaſius</hi> in his Creed ſaith: <hi>Whoſoeuer wil
<pb facs="tcp:5725:22"/> be ſaued it is neceſſarie that hee hold the Catholicke Faith, which Faith vnles a man beleeue in all pointes, and euery article, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>he ſhall periſh euerlaſtingly.</hi> One point is (good Siſters) that Chriſt gaue vs at his laſt Supper, his owne bleſſed bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy &amp; blood to feed vpon in the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of his bitter death: he that ſaith it is not ſo, doth he beleeue in Chriſt? Doth he not in effect ſay that Chriſt was not able to do it, and by that reaſon that he was not omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t? For when the three Euangeliſtes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port it ſo plainly, &amp; S. Paul after them: <hi>Take, eate, this is my Body
<pb facs="tcp:5725:22"/> that ſhall be deliuered for you: this is my blood that ſhall be ſhed for you:</hi> Mat. 26. Mar. 14. Luke. 22.1. Cor. 11. What maketh a man to doubt but that it is ſo in deed O you wil ſay, I ſee nothing but bread and wine. If you ſhould ſee his body: no god a mercy if you did beleeue it: But Chriſt ſaide to Thomas: <hi>Thou Thomas doſt beleue becauſe thou haſt ſene: but happie are they that beleeue when they ſee not.</hi> Ioh. 20. Mat. 2.</p>
            <p>I pray you when the three wiſe men came from the Eaſt to worſhip Chriſt, what did they ſee in him? forſooth a young In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant, not able to helpe him ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:5725:23"/> ſucking his mother a poore car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penters wife, and that in an Oxe ſtaule: yet they fell downe and worſhipped him as God: Is it not as eaſie to beleeue the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt is vnder the forme of bread, as that Almighty God him ſelfe was then vnder the ſhape of a ſeely weake Infant? O good Siſters, vnles you beleeue, you ſhall neuer vnderſtand: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue once Chriſt his wordes, &amp; that he is almighty, and that he is able to do whatſoeuer he ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and you will thinke that all is eaſie: returne to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Church, and bee content to learne that which you know
<pb facs="tcp:5725:23"/> not, of them that will not for all the world deceaue you, and you ſhall find exceeding comfort.</p>
            <p>When Chriſt ſhall ſay at the latter day, as it were in this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Was it not of my greate kindneſſe that I left vnto you mine owne Bodie and Blood? and was it not of my exceeding goodnes and wiſdome to leaue it, not in the forme of fleſhe and blood, leaſt your nature ſhould abhorre it, but of bread &amp; wine which can be lothſome to no man? and you make me this gay recompence, ſaying that it was nothing but breade and wine, becauſe you could taſt nothing
<pb facs="tcp:5725:24"/> els in your mouth, and becauſe your new Preachers tolde you ſo, whom I ſent not? were not you chriſtned in an other Faith? Did not my Church <hi>which is my ſpouſe,</hi> Apoc. 21. and <hi>the piller of truth,</hi> 1. Tim. 3. alwaies teach otherwaies. What haue you to ſay for your ſelfe, but that you haue moſt vnkindly abuſed that bleſſed Sacrament and heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſtery, and make me a lyar, and deny my omnipotency, and therefore deſerue eternall dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation with all ſuch as haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued you?</p>
            <p>When Chriſt ſhall ſay this, will it not be a heauy caſe? whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:5725:24"/> 
               <hi>Cyprian, Ambroſe, Chriſoſtome, Auguſtine, Ierome, Gregory, Ber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nard,</hi> all the olde Fathers, now Saints in heauen, ſhall come &amp; beare witneſſe againſt you, and ſay that they taught other-wiſe? When your Biſhoppes that are now partly dead, and partly in priſon for the defending of this cauſe, ſhall condemne you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you did not follow theire good example? When your owne Doctours and Teachers ſhall not be able to anſwere for them ſelues, will it not be a pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull caſe? But I hope better of you (good Siſters) I can not mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt your good natures, but
<pb facs="tcp:5725:25"/> thar you will bee glad to learne the trewth which: Almightie God graunt vnto you for his deare Sonnes ſake, who died for vs: and that I maye heare ſome comfortable newes from you.</p>
            <p>Doe but fignifie vnto mee that you are content, if any thing be amiſſe to be better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed. Proue me what I can ſay for any thing that troubleth your conſciences: It ſhall be far better newes vnto mee, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue two lines from you to ſuch a purpoſe, then to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that your huſbandes were made Lordes, and you Ladies.
<pb facs="tcp:5725:25"/> He is rich that is in the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Church, and he is honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable that is in the fauour of God. Siſters if I might doe you good to God-ward, I woulde not ſticke to aduenture this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of mine to ſaue your ſoules, to come and talke with you: my body is not more pretious vnto me then your ſoules: how you are diſpoſed, and what you would haue me to doe for your ſakes let me vnderſtand by the next. Deale wiſely I pray you and warily, both for our owne ſake, and for our good friende this bearer: It is not reaſon that for his good will, he ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre
<pb facs="tcp:5725:26"/> any danger: God forbid, my truſte is in your wiſdome, that you will keepe this verie cloſe tell herafter, by reaſon of the great perſecution.</p>
            <p>The matter is waighty, and conſerneth both you and this bearer very much: bee wiſe and truſtie, and deceaue not your Brother that loueth you as him ſelfe, and therefore wiſheth by all meanes to doe you good. Saint Paule ſayth: 1. Timothy. 5. <hi>Hee that hath not regard of his own kindred, hath denied the faith and is worſe then an Infidell. Saint Chriſoſtome</hi> vpon the ſame place writeth thus.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5725:26"/>
            <p>
               <hi>If a man inſtruct ſtrangers in the Faith, &amp; ſuffer his owne kinne to continue in there errour with whome he were likely to preuaile moſt, becauſe they make moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of him, were it not a moſte cruell &amp; barbarous man?</hi> For this cauſe I write vnto you, &amp; wiſhe you all grace, al goodnes, al hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenly comfort: laſt of all &amp; leaſt of all, to proſper in this worlde, and yet I wiſh you that with all my hart at the pleaſure of God.</p>
            <p>Other good thing I haue none to ſend you but this, I will remaine in your debt for your gentle tokens. Commend mee to your ſelues, your louing huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes,
<pb facs="tcp:5725:27"/> &amp; your little ones, and when you haue learned to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue right your ſelues, bring them vp accordingly and teach them to feare God. Make much of this bearer I pray you, and ſaue him harmeles by your wiſe and diſcreet dealings. Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God preſerue you, and by his Holy ſpiritte lead you into all truth. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:5725:27"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
